Luna had arrived at the train to Hogwarts long before any other student. She had wandered through the train trying to find the perfect compartment, and she had finally found it. It was a small, crooked compartment unlike any other, since it shared a wagon with the small room in which the Sweets Lady kept her cart. As such, there were only three seats in the compartment instead of the usual six, and the small table was irregularly formed.
Luna had liked it immediately. After all, three was a far better number than six when it came to holding meaningful conversations, and the crooked, asymmetric arrangement seemed comfortable and inviting precisely because it deviated from the boring norm. She took a seat, closed her eyes, and began to daydream.
Daydreaming was an activity Luna had mastered. Within seconds she had completely forgotten her surroundings, instead recapitulating the properties of the Crumple-Horned Snorkack. It didn't take her long until she had a complete picture of the beast, its violet, scaly hide and yellow eyes with the peculiar w-shaped pupils. From there, she started to extrapolate. What would it eat with its thin, needle-like teeth? Where would it have to live, to get just the right amount of sun, which was essential to its metabolism?
Luna had already spent quite some time on the subject, which was how she had acquired her knowledge of the Snorkack's appearance. Most people wouldn't have trusted long flights of fancy, but Luna wasn't like most people in any respect. When she had mulled over something for a long time, examined all possibilities and eliminated everything that seemed implausible, she already thought it quite likely. If she then saw it in a dream, it was as good as true to her.
When Luna opened her eyes again, hours had passed and the train was already moving. A girl was knocking at the wall, since the compartment didn't have a door, relieved that she had gotten Luna's attention.
"Hey, is this seat free?"
Luna nodded. The girl didn't seem to trust observations very much; wasn't it clear as day that no one else was in the compartment, that there were no trunks stowed away besides Luna's, and that it was unlikely Luna was still waiting for anyone, since the train was already moving and Luna hadn't even had her eyes open to look around for someone? Maybe she just liked making conversation.
"I'm Lea. You're a first-year like me, aren't you?", the girl asked. Luna smiled a little, as this had confirmed her hypothesis; the girl did like making conversation.
"Yes, I'm Luna."
A few seconds of silence passed, which Luna used to study Lea. She had brown skin and frizzy brown hair, which she wore in pigtails. At this, Luna stopped. She could have obtained more details about Lea, her clothing for example, but that seemed like a waste of time when they would be wearing Hogwarts robes shortly, anyway. The other girl just seemed so ordinary and uninteresting compared to the things Luna saw in her daydreams, as did most people.
Lea tried to start the conversation up again. "So, what house are you hoping to get into?"
Luna shrugged. "I don't really care."
"You don't care? But the Sorting decides what sort of person you'll become, and even who you're going to be friends with!"
"I don't think I'll let a hat decide who I'm going to be friends with. And I'm sure that the qualities of the houses aren't as set in stone as people believe they are."
"But you can't just not care! What if you end up in Slytherin? Everyone in the other houses would avoid you, so all your friends would be Slytherins, and that's the first step to becoming evil. You don't want to end up evil, do you?" Lea's voice had grown louder, which Luna honestly didn't understand.
She decided to pacify the other girl. "I am who I am, and no House would change that. Also, based on previous experiences, it doesn't matter at all where I end up, I won't have many friends, anyway."
This did have the effect Luna had been hoping for: Lea grew quiet. After a moment, she spoke again, though this time in a calmer voice. "I think you're going to end up in Ravenclaw. It's the way you talk, you know? And don't worry about making friends. There's someone for everyone, and once you find them, you'll be more happy.
Anyway, I'm hoping for Gryffindor myself."
Luna was a bit confused. Why had Lea assumed that she was worried and unhappy? Try as she might, Luna couldn't see a reason for anyone to assume that, and besides, it was wrong - Luna had been quite lonely for the last two years, and she didn't feel as though she was missing anything of importance. Though the company was a fine thing, she also appreciated having a bit of peace and quiet to think.
A few quiet minutes passed. Lea began to fidget, which was distracting, so Luna closed her eyes. She had just begun to pick up her train of thought about the Crumple-Horned Snorkack again when the Sweets Lady came around and readied her cart.
"Good morning, little ladies. How about a chocolate frog?"
"I'll take one", Lea said.
Luna just shook her head. It had always seemed wrong to her to enchant chocolate to resemble a live animal. Was it indicative of a deeply-held desire among wizards to eat living frogs, which they could only indulge in in this form, since it circumvented a taboo on actually capturing and killing real frogs? She wondered if the chocolate frogs would sell better if their insides were closer to a real frog's.
By the time she had gotten to that thought, Lea had already torn open the package.
"Another Dumbledore! They must put him in like every other package, I've already got ten of him."
Luna, meanwhile, was staring at the frog, which had hopped to the middle of the small table and seemed to be looking for an escape route.
"Do you think they have feelings?"
Lea seemed taken aback. "Luna, they're made of chocolate!"
"Look at the small thing. It's like he wants to escape. Of course, you could say it's driven by instincts, but that's just semantics, isn't it?"
Lea was quiet for a second, then she sounded angry. "You've got to make it all weird, don't you? I've lost my appetite."
"If you honestly think you wouldn't eat it now, how can you want to have eaten it without thinking?"
Luna reached out slowly, stroking the frog with her fingertips. It was cool and smooth, and though the chocolate was getting soft and sticky under Luna's touch, it didn't feel wet, as a real frog would have.
"Well, aren't you a curious little thing?"
The frog quivered slightly under her touch, as though it had understood her.
Then it exploded.
Within a split second, it went from being a reasonable approximation of a common frog to a horrid mess splattered around the entire compartment. Part of it must have been liquid, since solid chocolate wouldn't have spread quite that thin, and as Luna looked closely, she could see that there were more solid parts sticking to some of the larger stains, formed like small tubes and pebbles.
Lea was wiping at her face with a tissue.
"That's it!", she declared, obviously indignant. "You've been weird from the beginning, but making a chocolate frog explode, after you've almost convinced me that it had feelings? That's more than weird, that's twisted. You're going to end up in Slytherin and I'll be glad that I won't have to sleep in the same dorm as you!"
She stood there for a few seconds, out of breath after her outburst. When Luna didn't answer at all, she finally turned around on her heel and marched away.
Luna, meanwhile, was completely engrossed in watching what seemed to be tiny bones and organs in the remains of the frog. Ordinarily, chocolate frogs didn't contain any of those parts; they were made of solid, homogeneous enchanted chocolate. If one disregarded that this one frog might have been aberrant, which would have been a startling coincidence, something had changed its composition, likely directly before causing it to explode.
Luna knew it couldn't have been herself. She didn't know any magic with those effects and likely wouldn't be powerful enough to cast it. Accidental magic was more than unlikely as well. Firstly, because she had gotten her wand a few days back, and accidental magic usually didn't occur after that, since a wand was a powerful symbol of control over magic, or so went the theory, at least. The second reason was, once again, the complexity of the enchanted frog: Usually, accidental magic changed things to a simpler state or produced chaos, and it wasn't good at interfering with the structured magic of an enchanted frog.
Her next guess would have been an invisible older student pranking them. However, she still remembered having thought about chocolate frogs with realistic innards without telling Lea anything. A prankster would have been more likely to just explode the frog without any embellishment.
Therefore, something was here which knew how to work complicated magic, was invisible and could read her mind. A thought should suffice, but Luna liked the dramatic tension of announcing her conclusion out loud.
"I know you're there." Even among the many sounds of the train, her voice resounded in just the right way: Silent and ominous. Luna smiled.
And was thoroughly surprised when Ginny Weasley came around the corner, looking slightly embarrassed. "Hey Luna. I didn't know whether to come in, you seemed busy."
"Oh, hi Ginny. Take a seat, don't mind the froggy mess."
Ginny sat down. After a moment's study of the chocolate stains, she took out a handkerchief. "Do you mind if I clean that up?"
Luna opened her mouth, but in the tiny interval before she started to speak, a thousand colorful lights exploded behind her lids. She seized up and everything went black.

"Luna, are you alright?"
Luna woke up, torn from a black, dreamless sleep. Ginny's forehead was creased, her eyebrows lifted in the middle. Luna took a second to decode the expression and decided it was worry. She smiled her soft, slightly dazed smile.
"Yes. Just a bit tired."
It was an easy excuse because no one could have looked into her head to check. Headaches worked the same way. No one could do anything about lack of sleep or a headache, and so no one did anything, leaving her alone with the raging chaos. Luna closed her eyes again.
"Luna, it's not usual to fall asleep mid-sentence. Has this happened before to you?"
"It does, sometimes. But I've already been to a -"

"Most unusual. Most unusual indeed."
"Do you understand what it is she suffers from?"
"It seems to be a disease of the mind. I will have to consult with my colleagues."
Blurred colours snapped into focus for a second as the healer hurried out of the door, leaving Luna alone with her Father. Xenophilius Lovegood turned towards his daughter, worry and hurt etched deep into the lines of his face.
"I can't lose you, Luna. Not you as well."
He pulled Luna into a hug, but by that point, she was already gone again, her body but a shell as her mind soared onto greater heights. What would she have answered, had she had time enough to answer him? "Don't worry"? That was part of it, she decided, and lost that train of thought.

"- healer, and they said they couldn't do anything. It's not too bad."
Luna watched Ginny's forehead grow smooth again, and decided to close her eyes to get a bit more rest.
"You know, Luna, I really don't think you should fall asleep on the train to Hogwarts. What if you're still half asleep when they sort you, and you are put in Hufflepuff as a result?"
"I don't think the Sorting Hat is that easy to fool, Ginny."
"Wait, they let a hat sort us? Who told you that? My family refused to tell me anything!"
"I don't know, I must have read it somewhere."
"Hmm." Ginny looked thoughtful. "You like reading? I don't remember that about you."
"Oh, I don't know. I just pick some things up." In fact, now that she thought about it, she couldn't remember at all where she had read about the Sorting Hat, but memory was strange like that, sometimes.
"Wouldn't it be nicer if they just let us make the decisions ourselves?"
"You know yourself well enough to decide something that important?"
"Sure. If you're so confused that you don't know what you want out of your life, just look into a magic mirror or something. Ron told me there was one in Hogwarts."
Luna opened her eyes, startled. Something about the concept seemed eerily familiar.
Ginny misunderstood her surprise and backpedaled: "Not that I think you're confused, or that I was talking about you particularly! I meant more of a general you."
Luna closed her eyes again, trying to concentrate. The Sorting Hat, a mirror, how did those two fit together?
"Hey, Luna?" Once again, Ginny had misunderstood her. "Please don't be mad at me. I didn't mean anything by it."
Luna looked at her, and for a second, she saw Ginny as she really was: A young girl desperately in need of a friend who saw her as herself, and not just as part of a large family. The moment passed, but for once, Luna knew exactly what to say. "We're friends, Ginny, and nothing could change that."
Then, the exhaustion from her earlier blackout caught up with her, and it was easier to pretend to be asleep for the rest of the train ride.

"I'm scared, Luna."
Ginny stood close beside Luna, whispering to her so that the rest of the waiting first-years couldn't hear her. Why did she care?
"I am too, Ginny."
"What if the Sorting Hat puts us into different Houses?"
Luna was baffled. "That's what you're scared of?"
"Yes, of course!" Ginny's voice had risen above a whisper in outrage. "Don't you want to spend our time at Hogwarts together?"
"Oh, of course. But what does the Sorting have to do with that? We'll have some classes together even if we aren't in the same House."
"Well, if you are so sure of that, what are you scared of, then?"
Luna looked at Ginny's small, freckled face, studied the curve of her eyebrows and the way her eyes were tightened, but she didn't understand. Was Ginny still frightened or angry, now? Had Luna said something to hurt her, and if so, what could she say to undo it? Why were emotions always so hard to understand? But time was ticking by in the world outside her head, and her long pause would seem strange by now, so she had to make a choice.
"I'm scared of an invisible thing which can read my thoughts. It showed itself on the train and made Lea leave, and I don't know if it's followed me. For that matter, I can't be sure I've ever been truly alone at any point in my entire life, but now I know it's there and it can act on reality and I - "
She managed to stop herself at that point. Ginny was now a step away from Luna and not looking directly at her, anymore. The other first-years around them were turned in Luna's direction, but they also stared blankly, unfocused. What did this mean? Luna could feel her heart beat faster. She was interacting with people she had never seen before, and they were all doing exactly the same thing, so it was likely an emotional cue she hadn't picked up on. The possibilities overwhelmed her for a moment. Far from knowing how to act, she didn't even know what was happening.
It was a relief when the flashing colours came again and she passed out.

-~O~-

The Hat's voice woke her. It creaked like leather and settled like dust. It seemed like the voice itself was made of old age and the comfortable worn-ness of a favourite piece of clothing. Luna lost herself so much in the sound of it that she had no chance to make out the words.
"I'm sorry Mr. Hat, could you repeat that?"
"I said, 'Oh dear. This has never happened before...'."
Luna felt an odd twinge at the words. "What has never happened before, you repeating yourself?"
"How could surprise at repeating myself be the first thing I mention, when you would only ask me to repeat myself afterwards?"
Luna thought for a second about that. The Hat had presented it as though it was supposed to be some sort of puzzling paradox, but she just couldn't see any contradiction. "Well, obviously you would be able to see the future of a student, but only while you were placed on their head. How else could anybody expect you to make the right decision while Sorting while still maintaining the privacy of every single student?"
"How else, indeed. Did it occur to you, Miss Lovegood, that I might just extrapolate from your current state of mind? Maybe I could even ask you what you thought about the Houses yourself. If all else failed, I would still have a millennium's worth of wisdom to rely on." The Hat's voice had taken on a sarcastic inflection, but it softened with the next sentence. "Even though I can't see the future, we will find the right House for you."
"What would be the right House for me?"
The hat chuckled. "Well, you have some choice in the matter. You might go to Hufflepuff, where you will find support to last you long after your seven years in school. You might go to Ravenclaw, since though others might not see it, your mind is sharper than most. Gryffindor and Slytherin, I think, would be less ideal for you."
"Why would I go to Hufflepuff for support, when Ginny will be in Gryffindor?"
"Ah, sweet child." The hat sounded weary with age. "Not all childhood friendships last forever, and if you would stay too close to young Miss Weasley, she would feel burdened by you. Haven't you begun to notice it yourself? The little sighs when she thinks you're not looking? She'll grow tired of guiding you, of taking care of you because you're lost in your own head."
"I don't think so." Luna's voice was firm with anger. "I don't believe in the present you're describing, and I don't think much of your predictions for the future either."
"Such anger! Gryffindor and Slytherin seem more fitting now, indeed."
"You've changed your prediction after a single rebuke from me? I don't believe I'll take your advice, thank you very much."
"Young lady, I don't like your attitude, and it would be wise not to talk that way to a being as old as I."
"I don't trust you. Never trust anything that can think for itself if you can't see where it keeps its brain."
The hat was silent for a moment. "Where did you hear that?"
"I read it in a book, I think. Does it matter?"
Somehow, Luna got a vivid impression of the hat shaking its head. "Different minds see the future differently, it seems. Though it's generally good advice, it doesn't apply right now, since you already put me onto your head, and I'm already inside your mind. Though it is a most formidable maze, it is as easy to change as any other."
For a moment, Luna struggled to understand what the hat had insinuated, then she shattered into a thousand pieces.
The Hat's voice woke her. It creaked like leather and settled like dust. It seemed like the voice itself was made of old age and the comfortable worn-ness of a favourite piece of clothing. Luna lost herself so much in the sound of it that she had no chance to make out the words.
"I'm sorry Mr. Hat, could you repeat that?"
"I said, 'Why, you've got one of the more interesting minds this old hat has ever seen.' But don't worry, I'm sure we'll find the right house for you."
"I'm tired, Mr. Hat."
"Of course you are, child. We'll be done quite soon. How does Ravenclaw sound to you?"
Luna couldn't think straight through the haze in her head. There had been a question she wanted to ask. "What has never happened before, you repeating yourself?"
The hat cursed. It was an odd curse, archaic enough to be quite incomprehensible, something about a frog, an eagle and a roll of twine. The hat took a deep breath.
"Wait, Mr. Hat!"
"RAVENCLAW!"
Luna opened her eyes slowly. At the Ravenclaw table in the Great Hall, students were cheering politely. As she made her way over to the Ravenclaw table, still feeling as though in a dream, she saw Ginny looking pointedly away and felt like a traitor. She took a seat at the table, not reacting to anything the other students said. If she had paid attention, Luna would have seen the way her classmates looked at her, would have heard them muttering. She didn't care, just as she didn't care about Ginny right now. She was lost in deeper thoughts.
By the time the next student got sorted into Ravenclaw, the others had already given up on talking to her.

"You're sure it wasn't Wrackspurts?"
"I'm sure, Luna. How could Wrackspurts have caused this incoherent mess of a past?"
"Well, they're - "
She was interrupted by Ginny. "If I'm understanding you right, Colin, you think there's been someone no one remembers in Hogwarts last year."
"Yes! Everything just doesn't fit. From the first day, unprecedented things happened. First, there was the incident with the Sorting Hat no one wants to talk about. Usually, when the Sorting Hat does something strange, we would expect a Sorting to be involved, and therefore, a student.
After that, there was a steady escalation of bullying, the kind that really hurt people. In situations like that, there's almost always a student standing up to the bullies, resisting the authorities' attempts to defuse the situation. Of course everyone remembers how David Monroe ended the conflict, but no one seems to remember how it was started.
Now, remember Battle Magic? Records of the first years' battles tell of armies with clearly defined motifs and intentions, as though they were led by charismatic leaders, but in the first battles, Neville and Ron clearly weren't the forces they later became. Someone else must have led those armies unofficially, but no one remembers.
Finally, there's You-Know-Who's second fall."
"What about his second fall?" Ginny sounded concerned.
"Do you remember anything about the first time he supposedly fell?"
Ginny looked at Colin as though she was slightly disoriented. "He... he disappeared. He was beaten."
"By whom?"
"I don't - look, Colin, those are all interesting questions, but there's got to be answers. Have you looked in the library? Have you asked any of the older students?"
"I didn't have to." Out of a pocket, Colin drew a piece of lined muggle parchment which was filled with his tiny, cramped script in faded ink. The edges of the parchment were slightly burned. "This was written in invisible ink. Nothing fancy, just lemon juice. It contains notes from interviews with Ron Weasley, Tracy Davis, even Neville Longbottom. There are all kinds of little contradictions and obvious holes. It's impossible to establish a timeline of last year, it just doesn't have anything in common with a reasonable story at all!"
"So... you did ask the older students?"
"Obviously, but I don't remember any of it!"
Ginny was dumbstruck, and Colin was clearly scared out of his mind. Luna had to restore sanity to the situation.
"Wrackspurts explain everything. They confuse and confound, and in retrospect, large flocks of wrackspurts have been behind every conspiracy of the modern wizarding world."
Ginny rolled her eyes. "That's nice enough, Luna, but I really have to go. I don't want to miss lunch."
When they were alone, Colin grabbed his temples as though he was nursing a headache. "Okay, Luna. At this point, you're the only lead I have. How do we find these wrackspurts?"
"Oh, it's simple, Colin. They're already here."
"I don't see anything. This hallway's practically empty."
"I can show you." Luna concentrated. She had had ample opportunity to practice, lately. Her mind's floodgates opened, and once again, Colin's eyes widened with fear. His eyeballs rolled upwards until only the whites were visible, and he fainted. As he lay on the floor, he kept on gibbering madly.
Luna picked up the lined muggle parchment and frowned. What had Colin said had been wrong with the story? Contradictions and holes. He wanted a coherent timeline. Right now, she had no idea how to fix this, but she was all out of lemons anyway. Maybe she would find inspiration on the way to the kitchens.

Inspiration came to her, at last, in a dream, as it always did. It was spoken by a hollow voice that belled forth from a gap within the air itself, a gap that opened upon a fiery abyss. Or at least, that's what the wrackspurt that relayed the message told her. Its many mouths quivered, shaping infinitely small sounds that fell together into a coherent name. "Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres", it said.
And just like that, everything fit.
Luna woke with a start, and began to write. From time to time, she had to squeeze fresh lemon juice, and the bad light in the Ravenclaw common room made it hard to see. Besides all that, Colin Creevey's handwriting really was terrible as well as terribly exhausting to imitate. However, her inspiration was transfixed. She didn't forget a single facet of the absurd story she had seen in her dream, packing it all into fictional interviews with those whom she now knew as Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres trusted lieutenants, his enemies and his admirers. And what a story it was! It had an ancient and mad wizard, a sidekick with the makings of a true hero and a protagonist who was so deeply flawed that he had managed to convince not only himself he was right, but also the universe itself.
Luna wrote the last line on a sheet that still seemed as empty as when she had begun. This time, she was truly proud of herself. Though she still had no intuitive sense of plot holes and contradictions, she had the vague feeling that Colin would believe this one.

The very next morning, she snuck the paper into Colin's pocket when he was eating breakfast. She spent the day giddy with anticipation. Though her classes were, as always, filled with systematic misinformation planted by several conflicting secret societies, and her classmates hardly could have cared less for her, she didn't stumble. This time, Colin would believe the false secret, and then, she could tell him about all the real secrets no one ever believed her about.
It was soul-crushing on several levels when she found his petrified body with the piece of paper still stuck in his pocket. Of course, she took it back. If the wrong person found it on him, they would just throw the empty and crumpled piece of parchment away, and it held too much meaning to just let someone do that.
Luna went on with her day. It hadn't even occurred to her to tell someone about Colin's petrification.

At night, she had the strangest dream. It was tranquil, unlike her usual dreams, in which strange shapes and colours fought for attention with shrill sounds.
She was in her dorm at night, and a boy was sitting on the edge of her bed, face turned away from her. Somehow, it didn't seem like she had anything to fear from him, though his face was obscured under a veil of shadows.
"Luna Lovegood. You just might be the most extraordinary student among the first-years."
"I am?" Truth be told, Luna hadn't ever paid enough attention to the other first-years to find out how extraordinary they were.
"Oh, indeed. I don't mean to imply that you don't have fierce competition, though. Colin Creevey, for example, was a most interesting contender until about this morning."
"Why is he disqualified now? Isn't he more unique, now that he's the only first-year made of stone?" Sarcasm wasn't something Luna employed, ever. She was honestly curious about the criteria of uniqueness her visitor employed.
"He won't be the only one for long, if this petrification proliferates." The figure chuckled. "But let's hope it doesn't come to that. If you do your best, a catastrophe might still be prevented."
"You don't have to worry on my account, I'm always doing my best."
The visitor put his hand to his forehead, his fingers flattening the shadows. "I'm trying to imply something here, can't you just try to drop some subtle hints that you understood what I was really getting at?"
"Why can't you just tell me? It would certainly lead to fewer misunderstandings."
"Okay. I'll need a moment, though, I have to salvage the dramatic tension."
"Take your time, I'll be here the entire night."
After a minute, the figure spoke again. "It falls to you, Luna Lovegood, to save Hogwarts from certain doom! If you choose to help me, you will become... a double witch!"
"A double witch? Now that's silly."
The boy sounded really exasperated now. "Yes, my public speaking abilities have deteriorated over the past few months of isolation. Are you in or not?"
"That depends. Do you think Crumple-Horned Snorkacks are responsible? I don't think I could fight them. I don't think I even have a chance at finding one."
"Don't you suppose this is rather the domain of Wrackspurts?"
"If it was Wrackspurts, we wouldn't even have found a trace of Colin. They're secretive." Luna pointedly ignored the dry sarcasm in the boy's voice.
"You learn something new every day. I do think you should be more inquisitive from now on, though. You didn't even ask me who I was."
"That's just because you're obviously Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres. Sneaking into a girl's bedroom is your way of convincing yourself that Dumbledore was your true mentor, not Quirrel. You should write a message or two in my potions book, while you're at it."
"Ah." For a second, the boy was at loss for words. "That's certainly... insightful."
"Luna Lovegood, amateur sleuth, at your service. Now if you would excuse me, I have to get up early tomorrow. There are mysteries to be solved."
It had been a strange dream indeed, but there wasn't any doubt in Luna's mind that it had been true. Prophetic dreams were often the strangest, after all. So she set out to investigate, first thing in the morning. After all, if Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres thought it was important, there were no two ways about it.

Luna woke up, her memories of dreaming a vague, blurry thing. By the time she was fully awake, only a vague impression of complexity remained. A dream within a dream, maybe. She shook her head and forgot about it.

At first, Luna had been all too content to write the two boys' behaviour off as something she just wouldn't ever understand, but halfway through dinner, she changed her mind. That kind of attitude was just wrong, no matter what it was about. Curiosity was to be sated, and giving up just because you didn't understand yet was the height of weakness.
Back in the common room, she sat cross-legged on her bed. It was the posture in which she always fought her most complicated mental battles; not because of any inherent geometrimystical properties of crossed legs, but simply out of habit. Now that she thought about it, though, maybe crossed legs had geometrimystical properties. It would go a long way towards explaining why she had won so many of those complicated mental battles. She started on a few mental sketches of geometrical classifications of different postures containing crossed legs, until she noticed that she was distracting herself and decided to put it off. She would think about it first thing next morning, she decided. After all, if she didn't, it would distract her every time she crossed her legs, which was, after all, when she had to fight her most complicated mental battles.
She closed her eyes, breathed deeply and tried to slow her pulse. Finally, she felt she was ready, and pulled up her memories on what happened in that corridor. She remembered not looking where she was going, when she had walked into one of the boys, just a bump with her shoulder. He'd said "Hey!", and as he'd looked at her, there had been a moment of realization on his face. Okay, that was something to work with.
He had realized something right as he looked at her, had had some kind of idea.
Luna was at a loss for how to find out what kind of idea he had had. There was an almost infinite scope of possibilities there.
How could she know what kind of idea someone else had gotten? Well, how did she know when she had an idea herself?
When she had an idea herself, she would know more after the idea than before, and usually think about something different, which would, most likely change her actions as well. Luna smiled an inward smile. It didn't show on her face, but it felt warm and fuzzy anyway. She deserved it because she had figured out something by assuming other people thought like she did, and yet it felt right. This was a rare thing to happen, and when it did, it reinforced her feeling of companionship to humans in general in a most pleasing way.
Now, before the idea the boy had said "Hey", and afterwards he had complained about for a long time about how Luna had hurt him by walking into him. This was somewhat confusing, since Luna really wouldn't expect to hurt anyone by walking into them. So the boy was either exceedingly fragile, or he had been lying.
Lying had always been a rather difficult topic for Luna to wrap her head around. For her, there weren't many intermediate steps between thinking and saying something, and the thought of thinking about what you were saying beforehand to create untruths was just weird. In this case, though, it seemed the more likely hypothesis.
So the boy had been lying when he had complained. Why? He had expected to gain something from it, but you couldn't gain a lot by speaking. Basically, you could only influence people. And since Luna was the person he had been talking to, he must have been trying to influence her.
What had he been trying to get her to do? He'd asked for an apology shortly after talking to her, but he hadn't been content with it, anyway, so that couldn't have been it. After that, both of the boys had pushed her around while calling her names, behaviour Luna still found more than puzzling.
She wasn't getting anywhere with this, and she was getting upset thinking about it. In fact she had half a mind to just stop this whole train of thought now. She might have even done it, if the other half of her mind hadn't remembered her mother's words in that exact moment. "Think longer about thinks and you'll understand them."
And her mother had been right. If Luna hadn't started to think longer about things, she never would have found out about so many things. Basic, boring facts that she had badly needed, at first, like how to cook, clean and do the other housework which her mother had used to do. Then, as she invested more time, she had arrived at such wonderful things as the anatomy of the Crumple-Horned Snorkack, which was truly improbable and her pride and joy. Once, she had even understood a deep secret, namely, why her father always looked so disheveled since her mother was gone.
She was frustrated, and she was angry at herself, and she might even be a little sad, but there was a way out of these bad feelings, and it went through understanding. So she began to think again, and this time, by some instinct, she started in the middle. The boys had pushed her around and called her names. Luna was always bad at remembering faces, so she didn't know what sort of expressions they had worn while doing that, but she was good at remembering sounds, and she remembered laughter in the air. Since she clearly hadn't been happy, it must have been the boys. If they had been happy, what they had been doing had probably been their purpose from the beginning.
Now, pieces of the puzzle fell in place. Luna still didn't understand the first thing about the things the boys had said before that, or why the one she had walked into had pretended to be hurt, but she knew what it was called when people found enjoyment in pushing others around and calling them names. It was bullying. She had been bullied.
With that word, she understood so much at once that she barely had time to notice it all. She understood how she herself had felt, both directly after what had happened and when she had forced herself to think about it. She understood why the few people walking by at the time had pretended not to have seen anything, and she even understood why Professor McGonagall had talked about bullying while they had been in her office.
The elation faded when she combined her realization with what she already knew. The boy she had walked into had recognized her and bullied her afterward. So he probably wouldn't have bullied anyone else. She remembered what Professor McGonagall had said: "They'll grow bored of ignoring you." So this was it, then? They had grown bored of ignoring her already and so she was a target now.
Somehow, this made Luna intensely angry. She didn't think she had been that angry before, and she didn't even know what she was angry at. Part of her was angry at everything, part of her was angry at the bullies, but that wasn't the biggest part. The biggest part was angry at herself. She couldn't help shake the feeling that she was different, she knew she was different, and that was what had made them bully her. The complex dance of social interaction had never been something Luna had understood very well, and with the way she had just ignored all conventions, people had probably singled her out from the start. In other words, she had made missteps. She had tread on others' feet and ignored the rhythm entirely, and when she had finally literally walked into someone, that had been the step that broke the camel's fetlock.
In simpler words, it was her fault.
Oh, it wasn't entirely her fault, she wasn't that arrogant. A lot of the share of the blame lay on the two boys' shoulders, and a lot of others had enabled them. But Luna had been the one to take the first step outside of social convention, and when you did something different than a whole lot of people, there was always a chance you were just wrong.
That thought broke her out of her misery. It was just so, so entirely unlike her. When she was different than others, she wasn't necessarily wrong. She didn't think many people thought as intensely about things as she did, and she was quite sure, at the risk of sounding arrogant, of being the world's foremost authority on Crumple-Horned Snorkacks as a result. Before she could assign any blame to herself, before she could even think about changing herself, she had to think about it longer.
And in her haste, she had failed to consider something quite important. At the end, the boys had run away, and she knew now that this was out of the ordinary. They had been scared off, though Luna hadn't done anything. Therefore, there had been a third entity at work. Now, she supposed it could have been a teacher, but that seemed unlikely judging from Professor McGonagall's reaction. It could also have been a student, but she hadn't seen anyone do anything, and who was she even kidding?
There could have only been one third entity, and it was the one that had blown up a Chocolate Frog on the train. There was one coherent explanation for all its actions: It had wanted to do her a favour.
This, at last, reassured her, and a warm glow spread through her body.
Without thinking, she spoke softly: "Thank you, friend."
As she opened her eyes, she saw that the other Ravenclaw first-year girls had by now arrived in their dorm room and were, one and all, staring at her. She saw Lea's face twist in open disgust and knew that she had to say something to explain herself that would also seem brilliant and funny, but her mind was racing in circles and she just had no clue at all.
Before she could think of anything, bright lights exploded behind her lids and she faded away.

She awoke in a hospital bed, and it was already morning. Looking around, she saw that it was too small to be St. Mungo's, and therefore had to be the Hogwarts hospital wing. She hadn't expected to make it into the hospital wing within the first five weeks.
Something on a chair beside her bed stirred, and it took her a second to recognize Lea. She stared at the girl in open-mouthed surprise. Why was she at her hospital bed?
Lea cleared her throat. "I'm only going to say this once, so you better listen up. When the other girls and I brought you in, Madame Pomfrey told me you had some kind of mental illness. I have no idea how much of your", she scoffed, "behaviour is really excused by that, but I'm willing to give you the benefit of the doubt. If you promise to stop acting weird, I'll give you a second chance."
Luna took a second to process that. Maybe she was still asleep, since she hadn't understood at all what Lea wanted to say. "A second chance at what?"
Lea lifted her eyebrows as though the question was beneath her, but Luna, who had seen Professor McGonagall lift a single eyebrow, was not impressed and just waited until Lea spoke.
"A second chance at being friends with me."
Luna smiled an inward smile. She was pretty sure that she knew, now, what friends were. "I don't think it's really friendship if it comes with those kinds of strings attached."
Lea scowled at first, then shrugged. "Suit yourself, Loony. See you tomorrow in class, then."

Luna had no idea what she should do with the rest of the day, now that she was sitting here alone in the hospital wing with an entire day of lying in bed before her. She could think about something, but she could do that at any time when she didn't have anything else to do, like in History of Magic. It took a few seconds of thinking about thinking until she had an idea. She had a friend now, so she could just as well contact it.
Hey, she thought. Don't try to answer me on this, or I suppose I'll get knocked out again. I have an idea to circumvent that, but I guess you'd know. If you think it's a bad one, feel free to interrupt me with a seizure.
Luna waited for a few seconds, since she had noticed that interval with the earlier incidents. After there was no seizure forthcoming, she snuck out of bed, treading lightly.
Luckily, there was no one else in the hospital wing. Even Madame Pomfrey seemed to be away right now, and it was a short trip to the medicine cabinet. Of course, it was locked, since Madame Pomfrey was likely one of the most sensible persons in Hogwarts, but Luna knew just what she could do about that.
She put two fingers on the lock and willed it to open. Five seconds later, it sprang open with a click. Luna giggled to herself. This was almost as though she could do magic.
She looked over the bottles of potions and pills carefully, until she had found the one she wanted. She had no idea how she had known this was the one, but she was so used to correct conjectures just feeling right that she didn't even question it. She crushed three pills and took them with a glass of water. She knew, somehow, that this was a strong dose, but it would work just fine.
She barely made it to her hospital bed before she collapsed. Her last thought before everything went dark was that she had left the medicine cabinet open, but she trusted her friend to take care of that.

Falling asleep was usually a process so blurred that most of the time, Luna didn't even notice when she passed the border into her dreams. This time, the sensation was so abrupt and disorienting that the border might as well have been a wall of fire ten feet tall. She was falling, tumbling around in a manner not too different from Floo fire. Her eyes were open, and yet she couldn't see anything. What filled her vision was neither darkness nor blinding light, but something so nondescript that it evaded perception.
It was a relief when she noticed a solid object: A golden oval, filled with a picture. She fell forwards, and through it.

-~O~-

Luna Lovegood had known that she was different from the beginning. From her tenth year onward, she had known a truth no one else did: There was something seriously wrong with the way magic worked. Luna had arrived at this conclusion solely through reason and observation, though without her mother's death, her eyes might never have been opened.
After Pandora's death, the violent and completely unexpected outcome of an experiment that should have been harmless, Luna had sat down and thought. She had never been one for careful thinking, before, so she had needed some time to get used to the basics of concentration, extrapolation and verification, but once she had gotten there, the rest of the way was straight, if not narrow. In fact, it had been absolutely sprawling: The possibilities of explanation for what had happened were staggering. There was the possibility of a fatal mistake by Pandora, a rare statistical fluctuation in which a spell did something completely different, a magic-devouring monster or, even simpler, the possibility that Luna had simply gone mad and only imagined what she had seen.
The last option was quickly eliminated by virtue of being useless. From the inside, Luna would never know if all she ever saw were hallucinations, and if she assumed so, no correct course of action ensued. After all, she would have no idea how to actually see the real world, and no idea of knowing truth if she ever saw it.
Therefore, there was an external culprit.
The careful weighing of evidence took her months, and her conclusion was only reached when her wand chose her, at Ollivander's. It had taken Ollivander a long time to find her match, with many wands rejecting her, until he had, finally, with a worried frown on his face, brought her another one.
"10', Alder, core of dragon heartstring, rigid.", he had said. "I do not think, though..."
He had been interrupted by the wand giving of a powerful shower of sparks in her hand.
"Astonishing. I had judged you for the yielding type, yet this is the type of wand which chooses strong people. Do you have a goal to accomplish, one that might elude you for life?"
Luna had not known before, but in that moment, it had become definite. "Yes. To find the nature of magic." And change it, though she hadn't spoken that out loud.
Ollivander had raised his eyebrows and her father had chuckled. It was clear that they hadn't been taking her seriously, but it didn't matter. Luna had finally figured out what had happened to her mother.
It had been so obvious, in retrospect: Her mother had died of casting a spell. It was clear where the fault lay, no matter the intermediary: Magic. Something, somehow, was wrong with magic, when a spell could kill the wizard who had cast it. Be it through a small mistake becoming deadly, fluctuations in the effects of spells or even a magic-devouring monster, all of those could be fixed easily once she had found out just what was at the root of every wizard's ability to cast spells, and found out a way to change it.
With that realization, Diagon Alley made her uncomfortable. Magic was everywhere in this place, used for menial tasks and the tiniest of amusements. Now that she suspected any piece of magic might kill her, she didn't feel safe at all. Sadly, the trip to buy school robes and other supplies was far from over.
When they had finally arrived back at their house, Luna was relieved. Most wizarding houses contained about the same density of magic as Diagon Alley did, but the Lovegoods where, as always, the exception that proves the rule. Since Pandora's death, Luna had been doing her fair share of the housework, and since she was still underage, she couldn't exactly use spells to clean dishes, wash clothes, or sweep floors. In addition, her father had never been very good at that kind of magic, and so the greatest need for spells was gone. As in most other households, when the work was done, the rest was leisure, and neither Xenophilius (who was still very busy with the Quibbler) nor Luna (who spent the most exciting hours of her life inside her head) had much need for magical distractions.
As a result, Luna could breathe freely in their cluttered, sometimes messy home, without any fear for unexpected consequences.
When she stood before the Hogwarts Express a week later, she felt an almost physical pain at the thought of boarding it. She didn't want to enter a world so dangerously magical that even when everything worked as intended, students got hurt every day. Hogwarts even needed an entire hospital wing -
wasn't she there right now?

-~O~-

The thought pulled her out of the dream, and she stared at platform 9 3/4 through a golden oval framing it, which was floating in the middle of nothing. The picture in the oval still moved - the other Luna was boarding the train now, visibly fighting with herself.
Luna shook her head. This expanse of nothing must be where she went between dreams. Maybe another golden frame would appear with another dream, when she was ready to have it. Why had she never remembered this, after waking up?
Her curiosity spiked, and she looked around, though the nothing around her made her feel disoriented. When she had turned around completely, a different picture stood in the golden oval. There were no details in the picture, only blurry, wobbly shapes in various colours. Yet she could grasp its meaning.
Welcome.
Without even thinking, she answered. "Thank you."
She blinked, and the picture changed, somehow, while its constituent dots remained the same. It was a landscape now, depicting the sky in all its possible states of being, from huge, foreboding storm clouds to patches of clear and sunny sky. After a second, she got it. The picture was making small talk by asking about the weather. It was so unexpected that Luna burst out laughing, and when she had wiped the tears out of her eyes, the picture had changed again.
It was a sequence of objects now, each slightly different than the one before it, with the final one just being placed. Again, the question was somehow implicit in the composition, the choice of colours and the brushwork.
Another?
Luna nodded, and when she closed her eyes, she could feel herself being pulled into the frame again.

-~O~-

Muffled shouting could be heard from inside the locked classroom. Luna recognized Harry's voice, completely missed Ginny's significant glance, and would have walked right on by, had Ginny not opened the door.
The first few sentences of the conversation didn't even register to Luna, until she noticed that Harry's tone was quite confrontational, and had to intervene.
"You're being rather rude, you know." Truth was always best when friends were fighting.
Luna ignored Harry's even ruder response.
"Wait," that was Hermione, who could always be counted on to keep a cooler head than Harry. "Wait... Harry, they can help."
A short argument between Harry and Hermione followed, which was mostly about someone called Sirius being tortured. Now, this was either someone she didn't know, or -
"When you say 'Sirius', are you talking about Stubby Boardman?"
As usual, everyone ignored her more important questions, but Luna was used to that. She had already decided, anyhow: Obviously You-Know-Who would torture Stubby Boardman, most likely to pressure him to finally release a new album. You-Know-Who must be a fan.
"- otherwise I'm going to the Department of Mysteries right now." That was Harry again, still sounding quite rude. Why did no one ever listen to her implied advice?
Then she thought about what he had actually said. "The Department of Mysteries?" This was a location neither You-Know-Who nor Stubby Boardman were known for frequenting. "But how are you going to get there?"
Everyone ignored her, again. Then, they started making plans, which Luna was fine with. She had realized this was a priceless opportunity: She could walk into the Department of Mysteries on the heels of a perfectly reasonable - or at least sufficiently Gryffindor - attempt to rescue a celebrity in peril. The things she could see there...
She followed Ginny out of the room, her head swimming with ideas for Quibbler articles based on her fantastical discoveries. She would finally be able to unveil so many truths, find evidence for the Ministry's darkest dealings. After all, where could Fudge's secret Goblin breeding farms be, if not inside the Department of Mysteries? There were also the Heliopaths, the Aquavirius Maggots, and if she got really lucky and found the Hall of Prophecy, she might even find some hint for the location of the Crumple-Horned Snorkack.
Luna barely noticed that Ginny had started a commotion. Even when this much was happening around her - students running around, Ginny setting a distraction in motion, a daring rescue plan being implemented - her head was just so much more interesting than the outside world. She was running through everything she had ever heard of the Department of Mysteries and trying to compile a floor plan, or at least a reasonable list of the things they might encounter there. She didn't do this in the manner of one trying to account for possible dangers; rather, it was more like a kid planning a visit at an amusement park. There was so little time, after all, and so much to see, she had to be methodical.
She found it quite rude when Goyle grabbed her, completely interrupting her thought process, and told him so. Of course, she got ignored once again.
What was it with today? On most reasonable days, she could expect to get responses from people, even if they were, most of the time, curt and annoyingly narrow-minded. Today, however, she was getting ignored, cursed at, ignored again and even interrupted while trying to plan a visit to the Department of Mysteries.
Realization and horror dawned slowly. It must be Wrackspurts! The damnable little pests had snuck up on her and her friends, inciting irritation and confusion. Harry must be the worst off. She remembered his conversations with Hermione, how she had been trying to calm him down. He was the only one who had been sure of You-Know-Who kidnapping Stubby Boardman.
Suddenly, it was obvious that You-Know-Who couldn't really be torturing Stubby Boardman. More likely, he was a Celestina Warbeck fan; it fit his penchant for melodrama.
But Luna couldn't tell the others that, or the visit to the Department of Mysteries would be cancelled.
As she was being dragged into Umbridge's office, she was also getting entrenched in a serious moral dilemma. She had to choose between curing her friends of a serious case of Wrackspurts, thereby alleviating their worry and significantly reducing their chance of premature baldness, or visiting the Department of Mysteries and learning hidden secrets which were at the root of the Ministry's control of wizardkind.
Now, in case of moral dilemmas, one had to avoid two obvious mistakes: Thinking like a Gryffindor or a Slytherin. Far more clever was it to think like a Ravenclaw, and far more wise to act like a Hufflepuff. It would have been easier if theirs were not exactly the values of which this dilemma consisted: Attaining knowledge and helping her friends.
She weighed the issue for a few minutes, which wasn't easy - there were many potential variables involved in assessing the worth of a visit to the Department of Mysteries, since it was bound to be, unsurprisingly, mysterious.
She got interrupted again, since a fight had broken out in the world outside her head, spells and hexes flying through Umbridge's office. Sighing, she threw a few of her own into the fray, though her friends seemed to have the battle well in hand.
They were out of the office before Luna noticed that Harry and Hermione weren't there. She asked about them, but everyone was running, out of breath and in no state to answer her, so she just went with them.
On the way, she made her decision. If the Hat had sorted her into Ravenclaw, it must have wanted her to act like one. Though she wasn't proud of pushing the responsibility onto an article of clothing, it had to serve for now. A visit to the Department of Mysteries seemed much more fun, anyway.
When they had reached the meadows between Hogwarts and the forest, Luna gazed wistfully back at the castle, which she assumed she wouldn't see again for quite some hours. It struck an impressive figure, at this angle. set sharply into relief by the setting sun: The astronomy tower, the hospital wing - wait, this was a dream, wasn't it?

-~O~-

Luna stood outside the golden frame again. This had been a fun one - the thought of having so many friends was exhilarating. Of course, there were also the many interesting thoughts fourth-year Luna had had, and the prospect of an exciting adventure to the Department of Mysteries. Could this dream have been one of the future?
The picture in the frame answered her with a clear denial. Once again, the details were impossible to make out, with only the general meaning coming across, somehow.
It took a second for Luna to realize that she hadn't asked her question about the dream out loud.
"Have you been reading my mind?"
Yes. It wasn't a picture of the word yes, but it might have well been, for all its clarity in communicating the abstract concept of admittance.
Luna sat down, crossing her legs. Only after she had done so did she realize that she was still floating in midair, somewhat higher, now. Confusingly enough, she couldn't figure out how she had done it, without any firm ground. She seemed to simply have gone from standing to sitting without any of the intermediate motions.
Huh. This was her mind, after all. Though, now that she thought about it...
"You communicate in dreams and images, yet I don't think that you're my subconscious."
A dry chuckle. It was still visual, not auditory.
Luna just assumed that the other wanted her to continue. "You just wouldn't be up to the job. For once, you're not weird enough. But you have a sense of humor, or at least act as though you had one. And you can read my mind. The first quality is rare enough, but combined with the second... you're my friend, aren't you?"
Admittance. Though the brushwork in this one had been a bit hesitant. Was it shy, or just afraid of the consequences of revealing himself?
"I wish I could hug you right now."
Melancholy with a tinge of hope. It wasn't possible, at least not yet.
"So you can't communicate with me while I'm awake, only arrange coincidences. You can, however, talk to me in my dreams, after I've taken enough of the pills we've stolen from Madam Pomfrey. This doesn't explain where I got the idea that I should take the pills, though..."
Anxiety.
"Oh, don't worry, I'll take my time to figure this out after we're finished here. I assume you want to show me another dream, now that I've understood this?"
Luna closed her eyes and could feel herself getting pulled in again.

-~O~-

This was it. After fifteen years, she had finally completed her mother's work.
Luna breathed deeply and looked over her notes one last time. Her desk was stuffed to the brim with parchments, books both old and new, even stacks of muggle paper.
Not for the first time, she thought about the debt she owed her friends for their help with this: Ginny, for her encouragement, Neville, for his support, and most of all, Hermione, for putting her on the right track so many times.
She had pointed her in the direction of arithmancy, when she hadn't known where to start. Though Luna had, at first, had a rocky start with that particular discipline, Hermione hadn't given up on tutoring her, until she had mastered a solid foundation for spellcrafting.
After that came the hard part: Reconstructing her mother's work from memory. All of her mother's notes had been shipped to the Department of Mysterys and destroyed in a way so absolute that even Luna's memories of talking to her mother hadn't been the same afterwards. There had only been one thing left, which the Unspeakables had deemed unimportant. A drawing by a muggle artist, left behind the desk. It didn't seem real at all, since it was in black and white, and didn't move, yet it was still disorienting. Two hands were drawing each other, as though the artist had bent reality back on itself.
Luna hadn't suspected that it might have something to do with her mother's research, but when she had shown it to Hermione, she had noticed the connection very quickly. Luna locked fondly at the worn-out and dog-eared book on her desk. It was muggle-bound, soft cover, as they called it, which meant that it wasn't a real book at all. Though the outside hadn't hinted at it being a tome of arcane secrets, it had been astonishing and enlightening in its own ways.
Of course, after that, a more formal journey into the works of certain muggle mathematicians had been needed. It had been tiring, but enjoyable. Luna had learned many things about muggles which she wouldn't have suspected at all, among which was their ability to outdo even wizards when it came to inventing concepts that were completely incomprehensible gibberish. Some things in those books had been like spells whose instructions couldn't be understood until you were already able to cast them; like those spells, they had been amazingly powerful, if only in a very abstract sense. Mathematical proofs about the viability of proving things mathematically had only been the tip of the iceberg.
The real challenge had been applying those concepts arithmantically and using them for spellcrafting. Luna had brooded over her desk for months on end, painstakingly advancing in miniscule steps, only interrupted by the periodical frustration of Hermione looking over her work, finding wrong sentences in seconds and cobbling together far more sensible replacements in minutes.
Finally, she had managed to gödelize Lumos in a way that allowed it to be embedded in another spell. At that point, she was far enough into the matter that even the word "gödelize" didn't seem inane anymore. It was absurd how much more quickly her mom had arrived at those conclusions, and without the help of a muggleborn who was also the most brilliant arithmancer in centuries.
The last few months had been spent in the preparation of adequate security measures. She had spent a lot of time unearthing the painful memories of her mother's death, dredging them for any hints on how to contain the strange creature that might or might not appear when she tried to actually cast the spell. She had had brainstorming sessions with anyone who knew anything about magical security, as well as some so-called experts who really didn't.
In the end, they had decided to employ the sixth degree of caution, used with the most dangerous experimental transfigurations. Additionally, they had made sure they could escape. There were no anti-apparation jinxes in effect and they had even put a Vanishing Cabinet in the room.
They had done everything they could, and tomorrow would be the big day.
Luna lay back in her bed, content and smiling.
And heard the faint sound of scratching in the walls.

-~O~-

Luna stood outside the golden oval, shivering with cold sweat and fear.
The picture depicted three pieces of fruit arranged on a silver platter, all of them rotten.
"Three choices, yet none optimal."
Assent.
"You would have me take another path, then?" Luna wasn't sure she wanted that - the dream in the middle had seemed nice, with so many friends.
In answer, the golden oval flashed pictures of those friends, too fast for Luna to catch more than glimpses. Ron, sprawled on an old carpet, pale and dead. Harry, cradled in a crying Hagrid's arms. Then, Luna saw herself, locked in a dark basement, dirty and starving.
"Oh. I would like to avoid all that, if possible."
The picture changed once again, to a silver sphere reflecting the world around it. Once again, there was something more than the obvious in the picture, and Luna knew that the sphere represented herself.
The sphere was now dented, and the world it reflected warped, as well. Luna understood immediately, and knew that this insight on perception applied to all individuals equally.
The picture began to move now, though all the details stayed in the same spot. The dent in the sphere slowly vanished, yet the reflection was warped still. With a start, Luna looked at the scenery around the sphere and realized that it had changed to accommodate the unchanging reflection.
Luna hesitated. It wasn't that she hadn't understood the message. It seemed clear enough that the sphere was meant to be her, and the sequence of pictures had implied the application of some power unknown to her to effect her will upon the world. Her friend had shown her that she could escape her situation in any way she desired, though she didn't know how, yet.
The question was now whether she should.
As with any hard question, she shouldn't even try to find an answer quickly. This was something which had to be deliberated over days at least. She willed herself awake.

This time, when she strode through the golden oval, a single thought and wish filled her mind.

-~O~-

"I want to be needed"

-~O~-

"To be honest, I wasn't sure if I should assign anyone to this. It's been my private project for years; something I could just tinker with on my downtime, when other work seemed too tedious."
Luna, still a bit disoriented, kept on walking. Though Harry wasn't particularly tall, his determined steps still ate large amounts of ground. It was hard to keep up with him, especially here, in the deeper recesses of the Tower, where corridors were tight and twisting, and steps broke up the ground at seemingly random intervals. These rooms paid the price for the geometric excesses of the more public rooms, whose shapes were designed for maximum effect, not compatibility with the triangular shape of the Tower's base. Only Harry was really familiar with them.
"Are you still with me, Miss Lovegood? I honestly cannot tell whether you are listening to me."
"Yes, I am."
Why was he so distant? He shouldn't be calling her Miss Lovegood, not after all they had been through together. Not after Dumbledore's Army and the battle at the Department of Mysteries, where they had stood together as friends. Not after the hunt for the Basilisk, when she had served as his agent in a school that had forgotten him. She shook her head as if trying to clear it. Those timelines were mutually incompatible, and didn't fit with this one either, where Harry had had better things to do in his second year than hunting a mythical monster. Now, she was a researcher at the Tower, and though she had attended the Hogwarts Science Program Harry taught parts of, he hadn't had much personal contact with her.
Harry was opening the fifth door in a row, this one round and set into the wall a foot off the floor. "Well, here we are."
Luna looked into a small, polyhedral room that was horrendously unorganized. Workbenches and tables stood where the irregular walls permitted it, all of them filled with muggle devices and wizardly knick-knacks, most of them partially disassembled and stacked a foot high. The floor was not better off; whoever worked here hadn't cared about having space enough to walk. Once Luna saw through the chaos, she noticed the burn marks: Flames and explosions had left black marks on the stone of the chamber. She breathed in deep and wasn't surprised at all when her nostrils tingled with the residue of wild, untamed magic. Images of her mother came to mind.
While she was studying the room, Harry studied her. "It's somewhat embarrassing to have to show this mess to someone. What do you think?"
"It is messy."
Harry laughed. "No, I didn't mean to ask about the room. You might have noticed that I've neglected to tell you the nature of the project you'll be working on. So, what do you think you'll be doing here?"
"Is this a test, Harry?" Luna asked. Those who had graduated from the Science Program knew to expect the unexpected as far as tests were concerned.
Harry looked at her. She couldn't tell if he was taken aback by her familiar tone. "Oh, no, Miss Lovegood. This won't affect your employment at all, it's just to satisfy a private curiosity of mine."
Luna nodded. "I'll walk you through my deduction, then. This room," she walked into its middle, making a sweeping gesture, "contains piles of muggle devices. Though I don't recognize all of them, the electronic parts seem as sophisticated as anything I've seen in the Science Program. There are also some magical objects here, though they are rather unsophisticated; an enchanted lamp, a pocket with an extended space in it, some others. All objects not in either of those categories are planar in shape, or form containers. Now, from the fact that complicated muggle devices are near magic, here, and the way those other objects could be interposed between them, it seems obvious that these are experiments into preventing the breakdown of muggle devices near magic."
Harry was smiling, now. "Excellent."
"Oh, I wasn't finished. I've not taken the two most complex and mysterious objects in this room into account."
"Which would be?"
"You and me. You have been working on this for some time, or so the debris would suggest. Yet, you clearly haven't had a breakthrough by now. In hope for that breakthrough, you've hired me, and not a muggleborn, who would have understood the muggle devices in this room far better than I could. Also, I am aware of my poor grades in the Science Program."
Harry nodded. "Have you considered that I might just be short on staff and unwilling to commit those with better marks to a private project?"
"I have, and it's a boring explanation. Boring explanations have never gotten anyone anywhere interesting. You've hired me because of my tendency to think sideways. In the Science Program, I failed a lot of times, but I never chose the path that seemed obvious to others."
Again, Harry nodded. "So this is your answer, then? I brought you in to generate new, non-obvious hypotheses for this project on which I have exhausted the conventional approaches of research."
"No." At this point, Luna was having fun. "That still wouldn't take all the hints in the room into account. My answer is a question: What do you think is the nature of spells?"
"Ah. Your deduction seems to be missing a few steps, there." But the stern tone was a bad cover for the wide grin that had split Harry's face.
"Call it free association, if you wish." She had known since she had smelled the magic, but it had been fun to spin a large, roundabout tale of deduction. "Also, I couldn't fail to notice that your shielding materials have begun to gather some dust, though you have still been destroying muggle devices for a while. You've started to try magical shields, and that means you are asking yourself sophisticated questions about the side effects of spells. Before I can help you further on this path, I want to know what you think the nature of a spell is."
"A spell is a burst of magic shaped to effect a change in the world."
"You've sidestepped the question. What do you mean by magic?"
"It's energy." Harry's tone was pensive.
"But everything is energy, in the end, isn't it? Try to be more precise. What assumptions went into your attempts to block the side-effects of spells using magical shields?"
"Ah, I see what you're getting at. It's waves."
"Yes. You tried to abuse interference effects, but it was unpredictable, wasn't it? There was a random element in your results which no amount of careful calibration could eliminate. Your problem was that magic doesn't consist of waves, though it behaves similarly to them in some ways."
Harry chuckled. "Do you mean wave-particle duality?"
Luna took a second until she remembered the term. It had been explained in the Science Program, but only once, and like three quarters of the class, she hadn't really understood it. "Ah, no. The important word was 'behaves'. Think of it as a living thing, or more appropriately, an infinitely large number of living things, like an ecosystem that's so finely grained it might as well be continuous." In fact, that was not quite how she thought about it, but it seemed closer to the type of thinking Harry employed.
Harry folded his arms and raised his eyebrows. She remembered that gesture from one of his more condescending incarnations; it meant that he was pretty sure she was talking bullshit, but considered himself too polite to actually say so. When he didn't interrupt, she continued.
"There's a lot of those tiny things that behave in somewhat unpredictable ways. Though they might obey natural laws, they have free will. At the macro level, their tiny disputes fall away, revealing clear patterns, like history seen from a distance. The effects of a spell are deterministic. The side-effects, though, might not be."
Harry nodded, though he still hadn't lowered his eyebrows. "That is an interesting hypothesis, but for you to be presenting it as a matter-of-fact theory, there are some more holes to fill. Also, I can't help but wonder why I've never heard anything about this particular view from any of the numerous experts I've consulted."
Luna smiled an inward smile, and this one was deviously sweet. "Let's say that I've got the inside scoop on this." This was the closest she had come to mentioning Friend to anybody, and she knew that she was treading a thin line. "And I'm sorry, but you're not paying me to spill the beans on the nature of magic, you're paying me to solve the problem of destruction of muggle devices by magical side effects."
"What does your perspective provide in the way of experimental approaches, then?"
"We're dealing with a biological problem. There are two ways of warding off an infestation: The first is applying an appropriate poison, the second is introducing a sufficiently non-discriminating predator. I think we should just try to find something that eats the little guys."
"Yes, I tried that. The only creatures that are reputed to just eat magic are chizpurfles, and I've eliminated them as a solution since they only live as parasites and could never reliably shield an entire device."
Luna nodded, looking thoughtful. "I don't think those are our only option, though. I'll have to think about this. Oh, by the way, I don't think I'll need this laboratory, or any room in the tower, really. I'll just get back to you when I've found something."
"That's rather unorthodox, isn't it?"
"Oh, it is, but isn't that why you've hired me? I expect I'll find something within the week."
Luna left quickly. Had she stayed longer, she might have seen Harry's contrary posture fall away, revealing a wide, satisfied smile.

Within a day, she had thought of fourteen different candidates to test out, until she had remembered that she should constrain herself to beings that were already found, since they had to begin testing within a reasonable time frame, and there was no telling how long it would take her to find something like a Crumple-Horned Snorkack. Suddenly, there weren't any candidates left. The established field of magizoology was, as she knew, painfully narrow.
This left her with the interesting and unusual task of hypothesizing about creatures everyone else already thought they knew everything about.
She borrowed a copy of Fantastic Beasts and Where to Find them from the Hogwarts library, technically illegally, since she wasn't a student anymore. Some might have scoffed at her choice of reference, since calling it an introductory text would have been generous, but she didn't particularly care that it was short and written in a comparatively simple style. She had no use for long-winded paragraphs of description in flowery prose. In fact, she just needed a list she could tick off, so that she could be sure to have considered all options.
After three days of free association, she had her most promising candidate. She just had to look for creatures with improbably restrained eating habits, since those were the most likely ones to supplement their diet with magic. The Devil's Snare had stood out both for its likely capabilities of absorption and its ease of handling. At least, it had always seemed easy to handle to Luna; after all, it wouldn't be able to strangle anything which was bright enough.
Harry had been thrilled with her find, but somewhat reserved at her countermeasures, opting for a breeding program.
He had asked her to demonstrate the plant's powers of absorption. It felt weird, at first, to apply the experimental method to her own hypotheses, since she had done just fine with pure theorizing her entire life, but she recognized its use when she saw how quickly people were inclined to believe her.
Harry asked her to help him on another project right away. That project was followed by another, bigger one, and before she knew, she had subordinates, people who actually did what she told them to.
For the first time since her mother had died, she felt truly appreciated.

-~O~-

Luna was standing before the golden oval again. From the dream she had just lived, she had taken more than just memories. A deep sense of understanding filled her.
"It's a lie."
Question.
Friend was good with images; it could convey abstract concepts with its golden oval that Luna couldn't even imagine trapped in a picture, and when the picture was gone, she couldn't quite remember what it had been like. Sometimes, there was more meaning to be derived from the concept, like this time: It had asked a question, but it was up to Luna to find out which one. She assumed it had been a simple request for clarification.
"It's not real, this world I was/been/will be in." Her own speech was strange, sometimes, too, in this world between worlds. "This Luna has walked the path of the underdog. She has been ridiculed and underestimated, with bad marks slapped on her when no one understood just how clever she was. Then, she was given an opportunity to prove herself, and passed with flying colors. She has won the respect of that Harry, but that is not how it should have been.
It might have been like that for me, had I been in that situation, but the Luna that should have been there would have been different, and would have gotten praise and respect from the beginning of the Science Program. She wouldn't have needed to lessen Harry, and so he would have had the idea to investigate the Devil's Snare, and for a more robust reason than hers. This world is twisted, and this Luna is pitiful."
Three identical women in poses of agony and madness.
"Yes, I know, there is only one of me, and talking as though I were many fosters misconceptions. Yet my point still stands. I shouldn't change that world to contain such different paths to satisfy my own hunger for respect won against adversity."
Peas in a pod, each slightly different.
"Though it is a valid choice, it shouldn't be mine to make."
The peas were gleaming silver now.
"And we've been over that, as well. I still don't think I'm ready."
Golden chains, shattered on the floor.
"I... I don't understand." Sometimes, that happened, when Friend thought an unknown concept familiar to her.
Freedom.
"Yes, that much I had gotten. But who? How?"
Friendship.
Friend was probably growing impatient now, since it didn't like explaining himself. There were two entities Friend could mean with the notion of Friendship; Luna, who was its friend, or itself, because it knew how she thought of it. Luna steadied her thoughts and found the most probable option: It meant them both. Every conversation with it had to be taken in all possible contexts, if possible, interpreted in all different ways and seen as the sum of those. That was just the way it thought, and the highest barrier to true communication with it.
Choices, accomplished through Willwork, a prison shattered. Freedom for Friend, or friendship through freedom, or even freedom from friendship, as twisted as that sounded. After all, a golden chain could represent many things.
No matter what, Friend wanted her to act now, instead of waiting until she felt ready. And it would be discourteous to refuse; it had caused many good things to happen to Luna, likely at a cost to itself. It was time for her to return the favor.
The last question left was the How. It was ephemeral, though, before this golden oval. With conviction, Luna opened the door through which she had gone earlier, and let time flow. She saw what became of the Devil's Snare, once the breeding program had tamed it. It was little more than a potted plant that ate magic, and in fact, a potted offshoot of it stood in the greenhouse where it had been bred. It was an easy thing to reach through and take it.
Luna would go back, now. She knew that the time the five pills had granted her was almost up. But she would take this little plant with her and free herself, so that she might free Friend.

Mrs Norris had been found petrified some months ago, and Luna had been the only student in the castle who hadn't heard. Like a river parting around a stone, rumours passed by her, and though they tended to swirl and eddy in her presence, she didn't notice.
The attack on Colin Creevey had gone by, as had those on Justin Finch-Fletchley and Nearly Headless Nick. Though the school had been buzzing with fear and excitement since then, Luna didn't know anything. She didn't participate in conversations, and was just too absorbed in her own thoughts to notice things other people said or did.
Over Christmas, Hogwarts had been empty, the halls swept clean by fear. Luna had been planning to go home for the Christmas break from the start. After the first train ride to Hogwarts, she had resolved to seek out her crooked little compartment every time, and her peers avoided her, so she didn't even notice that the Hogwarts Express was unusually full.
After the Christmas break, everything was quiet for a while. Everyone was doing what they could to stay safe now, and caution seemed to pay off. There had been no new attacks.
Luna didn't notice. She didn't care about the behaviour of her classmates, be it the strange talismans everyone was wearing or the little mirrors some used to look around corners. Her classmates might as well have been of a different species; she didn't understand them, and had given up on trying to. There was no reason to attempt communication.
Besides, she was busy. Shortly after Christmas, after her talk with Ginny, after her second true encounter with Friend, she had woken up on a pillow stiff with dried blood. She had bled from nose and ears while dreaming of Friend, so much that she had felt slightly faint. In her right hand, she had held a tiny living thing, a tender, brightly green offshoot. She had done it; she had opened a way and dragged something through, something which shouldn't exist in this world.
Within hours, she had found the perfect place for her project: A tiny room deep in the dungeons. The unbroken layer of dust on the floor certified that not even the House Elves came here. The room contained no furniture and had no windows. It was perfect for her needs.
The rest was a matter of herbology, care and patience. Friend had shown her the way to a world in which she was a prodigy as far as plants were concerned, and though she had known that Luna had been a lie, just like the vision of research in the Tower had been, she had used her knowledge.
She spent hours upon hours in the dungeons, pruning and nourishing, cutting offshoots off the offshoot and seeding the room with them, floor, walls and ceiling. Her absence was noted - once, as she went back up to the castle, Dumbledore himself asked her to explain herself. She couldn't afford for her project to be interrupted, so she asked Friend to make everyone forget her, and it did. Suddenly, she was free of all obligations.
She devoted herself to her project. She didn't know what would happen at its end, barred herself from thinking about it, but the plant had to grow. Therefore, she went into the tiny room in the dungeon, content to spend all her time with the plant.
Though her skin had been fair before, she got even paler now, until the skin on the back of her hands became see-through. Her veins seemed green now, no longer blue. She slept dreamlessly several times a day, but never more than half an hour at the time, so her care for the plant wouldn't be interrupted for too long.
She didn't feel hunger anymore, though she was getting thinner and thinner. In some ways, she was happy about it; not needing food meant more time for the plant. This way, she only had to leave the room once every few days, to get more water for the plant.
While on such an errand, a group of Slytherins crossed her path. They were laughing and joking among themselves, but once they saw her, they stopped in their tracks. Pale and frightened, they turned around and ran. Luna got her water and brought it back to the plant, humming to herself. She knew why they had acted such. Luna had seemed like something truly strange, and their limited minds couldn't deal with the unknown.
It was as though they simply couldn't decide what she was; witch, ghost or something in-between, some cursed half-creature, and that fit Luna just right. She had always been different, she might as well look the part. With slight surprise she noted that she could really see through her skin, now, and count not only her veins, but also the vague shadows of the bones beneath.
She had forgotten her wand in her room, when she had last been there, months ago, and not missed it. Even if she had had it, she couldn't have cast any spell by now. She was as sapped of magic as any prisoner in Azkaban.
She didn't mind that the plant was eating her. It had grown so big that it covered the ground and walls entirely, now. Luna had put every last vine and leaf in exactly the right place, a grand design realized as a living thing. It had never so much as lifted a vine against her, and though she knew the exact steps of the breeding program Harry and her other self had conducted, she believed its nonviolence to be a sign of symbiosis with her.
To her, the confined room seemed infinite. Its size was not external, but within, a microcosm, sprawling scenery contained in the smallest details of the plant. She had explored so much of it, had charted so many details and mapped so many shades of green in the darkness, and yet there would always be more to find.
Above her head, the last blank spot of ceiling would close, soon. Only a few days and she would have created a space entirely free of magic, deep within Hogwarts. Then she could begin with the final, unknown phase of her plan.

The last leaf grew in minutes, accelerated by a sudden burst of ancient magic reverberating through the castle walls. Luna didn't know about the outside, about Hermione, who was petrified, or Aragog, not even the plight of Ginny, who was, by now, even farther away from the world than Luna. She didn't know that the Chamber of Secrets had been opened and wouldn't have cared. Her singular purpose had been achieved: Her tiny room was closed.
She had never felt as she did, right now. It was a feeling of elation, of completeness-in-lack, of asceticism brought to the cusp of ascendancy. With twitching, shivering fingers she could barely control anymore, she dug around in a pocket of the rags she wore, finding her most well-hoarded treasure.
Ten pills were left of the hoard Friend had gathered for her from the Medicine Cabinet. She took them all. Just before she faded, she knew what she wanted and hoped for: Without the interference of any magical background radiation, with her body a whisper on the wind, she could step halfway through the door, stay in the real world and be with Friend in the world-between-worlds at the same time. She didn't want to be alone anymore.
"Welcome, Luna."
Was it her state of delirium, that made her hear it speak in words for the first time? Maybe her dying brain put the pictures he always showed her into words. But maybe, just maybe, he was actually speaking to her.
And how intriguing his voice was! He took the ordinary words of English and formed them into worlds themselves, with jagged peaks higher than the highest clouds and deep, verdant valleys. There was life in his voice, ecosystems in a single world, a thousand species coming into being and vanishing just so he could make a single point.
Luna opened her eyes, and where the world-within-worlds had been a distant gray before, dull enough that she had never even noticed not noticing it, it shone from itself now, with subtle variation testifying to a long and varied history. She knew she saw Friend's soul reflected in his world, just like his metaphor of the mirrored sphere had always suggested. Her soul opened and sang with joy just as her heart struggled with its last feeble beats.
Finally, her eyes chanced upon him, and a black spear, jagged and terrible, drove into her open soul. She had seen him before; his iridescent claws, the inky pool of his blackness and the many things squirming within. Many things in the world-between-worlds had been lies, or only half-true, but this wasn't.
Suddenly, she felt so fragile, so cold and so small.
"Why?" She knew she didn't need to be specific. He would answer all questions at once.
"To get to this point. Every time you came here, I took from you and your world. Every time I did your bidding, our pact deepened. As I was the key to your chains, you will be to mine."
Suddenly she saw, hidden inside his darkness, a golden chain wound tightly around his squirming self. It was worn out and weakened, but it still held. In the center, buried deep within his mass, was a lock.
Luna wasn't surprised when she saw that the index finger of her left hand was a key. It wasn't a recent development. In opening the medicine cabinet for the first time, she had made it such, though she hadn't known at the time. It began moving towards the lock of its own accord, which wasn't surprising, either.
Power for power, and a key for a key.
And understanding for understanding, if she had her way.
"My mother pulled you free. But why did I see you in my dreams before you came?"
"My kind doesn't exist as simply as yours does. Echoes ripple across the world at our slightest movement. Have all of you forgotten whence your power comes, wizard child?"
"Wisdom is always fading. The magic all around us, even things of power... In another reality, I remember standing near a golden mirror, high above the earth, working my will. Yet I didn't notice that it felt as your touch did; the worlds rearranged as I wish."
Her finger was entering the lock.
"I had not known of that prison. You may ask of me one last reward, in fair exchange."
She smiled at Friend then, a bright outward smile. "That's not how friendship works." With a thought, her wand materialized in her right hand, pulled from one of the many worlds, and she cast as her mother once had; a spell in a spell, ad infinitum.